const e=JSON.parse(`[{"number":1,"question":"Which of the following statements does not reduce cognitive dissonance in a cocaine user?","options":{"A":"I have more chances of dying when crossing a road than injecting cocaine","B":"Smoking is worse killer than cocaine use","C":"Alcohol affects the whole body while cocaine is not that bad","D":"I like cocaine very much","E":"Even Freud used cocaine in those days, there must be something good about it"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"'I like cocaine very much' is likely to increase not decrease the dissonance."},{"number":2,"question":"At what age do children pass the mirror test?","options":{"A":"6 Months of age","B":"9 Months of age","C":"3 Months of age","D":"18 months of age","E":"12 Months of age"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Mirror test-A test for self-recognition in which the child using its mirror image to touch a dot on its nose is achieved at 18 months of age."},{"number":3,"question":"Which of the following increases the effectiveness of a persuasive communication?","options":{"A":"Mass media communication","B":"High intensity urging","C":"A credible communicator","D":"High receiver intelligence","E":"High cognitive dissonance"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The credibility of a perceived message is a crucial factor in persuasion."},{"number":4,"question":"Which of the following describes a self-serving bias?","options":{"A":"A person attributes other people's behaviour to internal sources","B":"A person attributes other people's behaviour to external sources","C":"A person attributes successes to external sources","D":"A person attributes successes to internal sources","E":"A person attributes failures to internal sources"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Self-serving bias-people show a strong bias towards attributing their success to internal causes while attributing failures to situational causes."},{"number":5,"question":"Which of the following factors reduce cognitive dissonance?","options":{"A":"High probability of unpleasant consequences","B":"Adding one or more alternative cognitions","C":"Awareness of responsibility for consequences","D":"Low pressure to comply","E":"Increased choice of options"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Dissonance is lowered if the behaviour is altered; cognitions are dismissed, and new cognitions are added."},{"number":6,"question":"Which of the following is true concerning primate psychology?","options":{"A":"Aggressive male baboons have longer life expectancy","B":"Aggression is higher during periods of instability","C":"Young baboons learn appropriate expression of aggression by observing their peers","D":"Low ranking baboons are not aggressive","E":"Among baboons, females are not aggressive"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"During periods of instability such as rank transition, baboons show higher levels of aggression."},{"number":7,"question":"Which of the following is most likely to influence individuals to conform to the views of the group?","options":{"A":"Other individuals being friends","B":"Older individuals","C":"Individuals feel accepted by the group","D":"Large group size","E":"Ambiguous tasks"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Ambiguous tasks tend to lead to more conformity as people may feel less certain of their own ideas."},{"number":8,"question":"Which of the following correctly describes fundamental attribution error?","options":{"A":"Refusing to accept one's own errors","B":"Denying the fundamental flaws behind one's own negative behaviour","C":"Attributing others mistakes to the context in which the mistakes occur","D":"Attributing one's own mistakes to one's character and personality","E":"Attributing others mistakes to their personal dispositions"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Fundamental Attribution Error refers to overestimating dispositional factors and not situational factors while attributing causes to other’s behaviours."},{"number":9,"question":"The theory of mind is not well developed in which of the following disorders?","options":{"A":"All of the above","B":"Anxiety disorders","C":"Psychosomatic disorders","D":"Depressive disorders","E":"Autistic spectrum disorders"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Theory of mind: An understanding that other people possess mental states that involve ideas and views of the world that are different from our own."},{"number":10,"question":"The first aspect of self-concept to develop is the","options":{"A":"Self actualisation","B":"Self efficacy","C":"Self image","D":"Self esteem","E":"Bodily self"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Bodily self-refers to the ability to differentiate one's own body from that of others."},{"number":11,"question":"Which of the following is correct with regard to cognitive dissonance? It is a:","options":{"A":"Type of medicolegal plea","B":"Phenomenon of group think","C":"Product of inconsistent cognitions","D":"Method of choice for solving abstract problems","E":"Form of thought disorder"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The principle of cognitive consistency is the focus of Festinger's (1957) theory of cognitive dissonance."},{"number":12,"question":"The individual behaviour of group members is less important than that of the whole group. What is this concept called?","options":{"A":"Group think","B":"Sociogram","C":"Deindividuation","D":"Risky shift phenomenon","E":"Polarization"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Deindividuation is a process where people lose their sense of socialized individual identity and resort to unsocialized and antisocial behaviours."},{"number":13,"question":"Individuals often tend not to intervene when someone seeks help, especially when others who can offer help are present in the vicinity. In social psychology, this phenomenon is known as","options":{"A":"Diffusion of responsibility","B":"Persuasion","C":"Bystander intervention","D":"Obedience","E":"Pluralistic ignorance"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Diffusion of responsibility: people feel that the responsibility is not theirs, and someone else will do something."},{"number":14,"question":"Which of the following is a behavioural component of Allport's concept of prejudice?","options":{"A":"Circumlocution","B":"Stereotype","C":"Discrimination","D":"Moral attack","E":"Hostility"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Prejudice is essentially an attitude. Hence, it has cognitive component – stereotypes; affective component – hostility; and behavioural component – discrimination."},{"number":15,"question":"In a small group situation, under which of the following conditions departures from norms are most likely to be tolerated?","options":{"A":"The setting is private","B":"Presence of strong group leadership","C":"The norms were stated frequently during previous meetings","D":"Dissent comes from a member with strong credentials","E":"A consensus was reached before the dissent was expressed"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Norm rejection is more easily achieved in the absence of enforcement and more readily tolerated if the rejecting member possesses strengths and abilities needed by the group."},{"number":16,"question":"Aggression is a consequence of frustration. Who proposed this hypothesis?","options":{"A":"The cue hypothesis of aggression","B":"Lazarus and Folkman","C":"Dollard's frustration-aggression hypothesis","D":"Friedman and Rosenman","E":"Lorenz ethological studies"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"According to Berkowitz, aggressive-cue hypothesis frustration provokes anger, not aggression."},{"number":17,"question":"A patient feels unhappy with respect to one aspect of his life. Soon he observes that this unhappiness affects several other aspects of his life as well, resulting in a depressed state of mind. Which of the following types of cognitive bias is most likely to be relevant to this description?","options":{"A":"Domino effect","B":"Recall bias","C":"Stockholm effect","D":"Hawthorne effect","E":"Attributional fallacy"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Domino effect is the psychological equivalent of the butterfly effect in chaos theory."},{"number":18,"question":"The attributional bias seen in persecutory delusions are","options":{"A":"Internal attribution for positive events","B":"Internal attribution for negative events","C":"External attribution for negative events","D":"Internal attribution for all events","E":"External attribution for positive events"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"It has been proposed that individuals with persecutory delusions make excessive external attributions of the cause for negative events."},{"number":19,"question":"The term 'cognitive dissonance' was coined by","options":{"A":"McClelland","B":"Schacter","C":"Festinger","D":"Beck","E":"Bard"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Festinger coined the term 'cognitive dissonance'."},{"number":20,"question":"The Likert scale consists of","options":{"A":"Three responses to each statement","B":"Four responses to each statement","C":"Five responses to each statement","D":"Six responses to each statement","E":"Seven responses to each statement"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"The Likert scale consists of five responses to each statement- Agree/disagree on a five-point scale."},{"number":21,"question":"In a social psychology experiment, audience attended a convention where speakers were randomly allocated to speak in favour of or against an important political issue. The audience were told beforehand that the attitudes of the speakers were determined by a coin toss. Despite this, the subjects rated speakers who spoke in favour of the subject as having on average a more positive attitude towards the issue than those who spoke against it. Which of the following does this indicate?","options":{"A":"Pygmalion effect","B":"Actor-observer bias","C":"Just world phenomenon","D":"Fundamental attribution error","E":"Hawthorne effect"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"We tend to explain behaviour in terms of internal disposition, such as personality traits, abilities, motives, etc."},{"number":22,"question":"Several people at a train station see an elderly man asking for help. None of the onlookers offer to help. This is explained by","options":{"A":"Group think","B":"Halo effect","C":"Risky shift phenomenon","D":"Genovese effect","E":"Group polarization"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"This is called bystander apathy or Genovese effect."},{"number":23,"question":"A depressed patient has shown a good degree of improvement in her sleep pattern after initiating a new treatment. Though objectively she continues to be depressed, when using a self-rated scale to monitor her symptoms, she significantly overrates the degree of improvement in her mood and other domains. This effect is called","options":{"A":"Drift effect","B":"Stockholm effect","C":"Domino effect","D":"Hawthorne effect","E":"Halo effect"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The halo effect refers to a cognitive bias whereby the perception of a particular trait is influenced by the perception of other related traits."},{"number":24,"question":"If a person's performance of a task is influenced by test procedures used, this is called","options":{"A":"Hawthorne effect","B":"Halo effect","C":"Pygmalion effect","D":"Practice effect","E":"Barnham effect"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The Hawthorne effect refers to the tendency of some people to work harder and perform better when they are a part of an experiment."},{"number":25,"question":"Which of the following accurately reflects instrumental aggression?","options":{"A":"It is often impulsive","B":"It is carried out using destructive weapons","C":"It is often planned","D":"It is motivated by negative feelings","E":"It is often purposeless"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Instrumental aggression is carried out for the purpose of achieving a particular goal, e.g., kidnapping for ransom."},{"number":26,"question":"Task completion is poor in which of the following types of leadership?","options":{"A":"Democratic leaderships","B":"Autocratic leadership style","C":"Controlling","D":"Rigid","E":"Laissez-faire leadership"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Task completion is good in autocratic and democratic leaderships but poor in groups led by a leader with laissez-faire style."},{"number":27,"question":"Vulnerability to conform with the group is more in those that are","options":{"A":"Less intelligent","B":"Self-reliant","C":"Expressive.","D":"Socially able","E":"Intelligent"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Less intelligent members conform more than those with higher IQ."},{"number":28,"question":"The vulnerability to conform is greater in individuals with which of the following characteristic features?","options":{"A":"Socially able","B":"Naive","C":"Very expressive","D":"Highly intelligent","E":"Self reliant"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"People who are naive are more likely to conform, especially to members of their own group."},{"number":29,"question":"Which of the following is considered to be a factor of social influence when a group makes a polarized decision?","options":{"A":"Normative influence","B":"Summative influence","C":"Disintegrative influence","D":"Authoritative influence","E":"Formative influence"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Normative influence: People have a need not to appear odd or 'stick out' as a sore thumb."},{"number":30,"question":"The classic studies by Milgram explain the concept of","options":{"A":"Social norms","B":"Persuasion","C":"Motivation","D":"Conformity","E":"Obedience"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"The classic studies by Milgram show that people would obey orders under certain conditions even if these exceeded the bounds of their usual beliefs."},{"number":31,"question":"Which of the following can reduce groupthink?","options":{"A":"Strong chairperson","B":"Financial incentives","C":"Unplanned meetings of the group","D":"Fewer group members","E":"Open debate"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Various strategies that can reduce groupthink include encouraging open debate and acknowledging the presence of groupthink."},{"number":32,"question":"A team leader is constantly calling for her group to focus on its commitment to the overall outcomes more than anything else. She is following a","options":{"A":"Relationship oriented style","B":"Autocratic style","C":"Persuasive style","D":"Coercive style","E":"Task oriented style"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Persuasion is the ability to motivate and enthuse the group to pursue the goal."},{"number":33,"question":"In a dark room, several lights are turned on and off in rapid succession. An observer perceives a single light as moving from one position to the next rather than different lights coming on and off at different positions. What is this called?","options":{"A":"Visual hallucination","B":"Pseudohallucination","C":"Cocktail party phenomenon","D":"Phi phenomenon","E":"None of the above"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"The phi phenomenon is an optical illusion based on the principle that the human eye is capable of perceiving movement from pieces of information."},{"number":34,"question":"Which one of the following is a secondary drive?","options":{"A":"Sex","B":"None of the above","C":"Play","D":"Food","E":"Water"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Competence or secondary drives are those, which people seek out, but which do not fulfil a physiological need like play."},{"number":35,"question":"The semantic differential scale may be subject to which of the following problems?","options":{"A":"All of the above","B":"Positional response bias","C":"Recall Bias","D":"Selection bias","E":"Performance bias"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"The semantic differential scale is a visual analogue scale that may be subject to various biases."},{"number":36,"question":"A candidate who has appeared for a mock exam before the actual exam does well than a candidate who has not. This is called","options":{"A":"Practice effect","B":"Hawthorne effect","C":"Observer effect","D":"Regression of mean","E":"Halo effect"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Practice effects occur when a participant performs the same task twice and can improve performance in the second instance."},{"number":37,"question":"What factor is the most influential in the development of friendly relationships?","options":{"A":"Complementarity","B":"Personal similarity","C":"Proximity","D":"Reciprocity","E":"Attractiveness"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"A classic study identified proximity as a major factor affecting the probability of making an acquaintance."},{"number":38,"question":"In Milgram's obedience experiments, the factors that increased obedience include all except","options":{"A":"Administering by proxy","B":"Relieving the subject from responsibility of actions","C":"Subject achieving an agentic state","D":"Proximity to the shocked victim","E":"Authority figure providing instructions"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Being proximal to shocked victim will reduce shock administering behaviour and so reduce obedience."},{"number":39,"question":"The most common effect of cognitive dissonance is","options":{"A":"Memory disturbances","B":"Formal thought disorder","C":"Cognitive distortions","D":"Psychological distress","E":"Behavioural modification"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Cognitive dissonance is an aversive psychological state aroused when there is a discrepancy between actions and attitudes."},{"number":40,"question":"The power in a person due to his ability to provide positive accomplishments is known as","options":{"A":"Expert power","B":"Legitimate power","C":"Reward power","D":"Referent power","E":"Coercive power"},"correct_answer":"C","explanation":"Reward power is the power that is conveyed through rewarding individuals for compliance with one's wishes."},{"number":41,"question":"Which one among the following is defined by how much we approve of ourselves and how worthy we think of ourselves?","options":{"A":"Self efficacy","B":"Self esteem","C":"Self image","D":"Self actualisation","E":"Self awareness"},"correct_answer":"B","explanation":"Self-esteem refers to how much we approve of ourselves and how worthy we think of ourselves."},{"number":42,"question":"Tom is a student who attributes a good grade on an exam to his intelligence and hard work but a poor grade to the teacher's poor ability and unfair test questions. He is exhibiting;","options":{"A":"Negativity bias","B":"Attentional bias","C":"Barnum effect","D":"Self serving bias","E":"Just world hypothesis"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"A self-serving attributional bias refers to individuals attributing their successes to internal or personal factors but attributing their failures to external or situational factors."},{"number":43,"question":"The presence of others reduces task performance. This is called","options":{"A":"Group polarization","B":"Group think","C":"Social facilitation","D":"Risky shift phenomenon","E":"Social loafing"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Social loafing is a phenomenon where individuals exert less effort when working as part of a group."},{"number":44,"question":"Attitudes do not always correlate with one's behaviours. The attitudes that most accurately predict behaviour are those that are","options":{"A":"Broad and not task specific","B":"Not emotionally valued","C":"Flexible and changeable","D":"Not based on one's own life experiences","E":"Strong and consistent"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"Attitudes predict behaviour if they are strong and consistent and based on direct experience."},{"number":45,"question":"Scapegoating refers to","options":{"A":"Tension between racial groups rise when the economic conditions are similar","B":"Encouraging conflicts with a political motive","C":"Sexual assault on a vulnerable group leading to conflicts","D":"Lack of empathy on perpetrators of abuse","E":"Captives becoming emotionally attached to the captivators"},"correct_answer":"A","explanation":"Scapegoats are singled out victims who are blamed and discriminated by virtue of their group membership."},{"number":46,"question":"A mother of an autistic child is curious to know the reason behind her son's apparent lack of empathy towards other children of similar age. Which of the following concept is relevant to address her question?","options":{"A":"Attribution error","B":"Cerebellar dysplasia","C":"Precontemplative stage","D":"Theory of mind","E":"Cognitive dissonance"},"correct_answer":"D","explanation":"Lack of Theory of Mind (ToM) may be the explanation for the apparent lack of empathy among children with autism."},{"number":47,"question":"According to the frustration-aggression hypothesis which of the following is false?","options":{"A":"Aggression is the one of the many possible responses to frustration","B":"Fear of punishment can inhibit aggression","C":"Aggression is driven by a need to nullify frustration","D":"Unavailability of the frustrator can inhibit aggression","E":"Unexpressed frustration cannot be displaced onto an innocent target"},"correct_answer":"E","explanation":"In a meta-analysis, evidence showed that frustrated individuals show displacement of aggression from the source of frustration onto a less powerful or more accessible target."}]`);export{e as default};
